Hi again.
In the previous video, you
learned about the value of data.
In this lesson, we'll discuss the common
types of data that project managers
collect and analyze regularly.
We'll also discuss the tools you'll need
to organize this data for your projects.
Ready to get started?
Okay, let's go!
As we discussed earlier, data is the
collection of facts that can help inform
decisions. You may start to notice how
the project data impacts the team's daily
activities and the overall progress and
the success of the project.
This is done by using
various types of metrics.
A metric is a quantifiable
measurement that is used to track and
assess a business objective.
Metrics are based on selected goals.
They vary per project and
serve as a key type of project data.
There are many types of project data
you can use to determine progress and
efficiency.
You can group project metrics into
productivity metrics and quality metrics.
Productivity typically measures
progress and output over time.
Productivity metrics allow you
to track the effectiveness and
efficiency of your project and
include metrics like milestones, tasks,
projections, and duration.
Let's break down each metric.
As you may recall from an earlier course,
a milestone is an important point
within the project schedule
that indicates progress and
usually signifies completion of a
deliverable or phase of the project.
And a project task is
an activity that needs to be
accomplished within a set period of time.
A projection is how you predict an outcome
based on the information you have now.
For example, you can predict that with
the resources you have at the start of
the project, the project will
be completed in six months.
The duration of a project is the total
time it takes to complete a project from
start to finish.
Duration can also be used for
milestones and
determining if you'll
meet project deadlines.
This data is broken down into hours,
days, weeks, months, and sometimes years.
So to recap,
productivity metrics include milestones,
tasks, projections, and duration.
Now let's discuss quality metrics.
Quality metrics relates to
achieving acceptable outcomes and
can include metrics such
as the number of changes,
issues, and cost variance,
which all affect quality.
Let's discuss each metric.
The number of changes during the project
or project scope helps to monitor risks.
Changes show any inconsistencies from
the initial requirements of the project.
A series of compounding small changes
may indicate a bigger issue and
provide early warning
signs of these issues.
Using a change log to keep a record
of these changes is a useful tool for
communicating with stakeholders about
why something is taking a long time or
costs more than expected.
A change log is a record of all of
the notable changes on a project.
An issue is a known and real problem that
may affect the ability to complete a task.
For example, an issue might be
the delay of legal approval for
an advertisement you
were hoping to launch or
the missing number of confirmed seats to
secure a venue for a business conference.
Another quality metric is cost variance.
It illustrates the difference between
the actual cost and the budget cost.
Simply put,
cost variance compares what you plan to
spend versus what you actually spent.
Let's put it in an example.
If you budgeted to only host 250 attendees
at an upcoming business conference but
275 people showed up and the venue
charges you for those additional guests,
the actual costs will be higher than
your initial budget or estimate.
So to recap, quality metrics can
include things like number of changes,
issues, and cost variance.
While these data points are commonly
tracked by project managers, there
are dozens more that you can leverage
to inform decisions in your project.
The great news is that there's
a lot of sophisticated software and
tools dedicated to project management and
data analysis,
so you'll have help keeping track of all
of these different types of data in one
centralized location.
Project management tools like
Workfront and JIRA track activity and
provide readable results
so you can measure the overall
health of your project.
Data analysis tools like Tableau
are useful for data visualization.
Now you know a bit more about how
to identify common types of data.
You can also ID common project
management software and
tools that can help you manage and
analyze data.
In the next lesson, we'll cover how data
helps you to make informed decisions.
Meet you there.